Hello, welcome. It is July 30th, 2025
and we're in Octrince guest stream 115.1
with Alexi Gladstone who will be
presenting and discussing energybased
transformers in the future of scaling.
There will be a presentation followed by
a discussion. So if you're watching
live, please write any questions in the
live chat. Otherwise, thank you Alexi at
all for the paper and the work and for
joining and looking forward to the
presentation. Thank you.
Thanks for having me, Daniel. Excited to
uh start this presentation. So let's go
ahead and get started.
And I'm going to ask a philosophical
question at the start of this just to
get everyone thinking. And we'll circle
back to this at the end of the
presentation. But that question is would
you trade off 100 times the amount of
computation. So burning your GPUs for
100 times longer for 1% better
generalization. Right? So generalizing
1% better out of distribution. Tiny
amount, right? And you might say this
question sounds absolutely ludicrous.
Who in their right mind would spend 100
times the amount on computation just to
do 1% better? And maybe we're already
actually seeing it, right? So this is an
example with opening ISO 01 and it
thinking for a very long time to
generalize better albeit maybe not 1%
better but this is kind of the insight
that I think will lead you into the
ideas behind uh energy based
transformers that we are going to dive
into now. So to give some
contextualization there's been lots of
interest recently in what are called
thinking and reasoning models broadly in
AI especially in language modeling. So
in language models particularly with
large language models we've se seen tons
of models in fact this slide is now
outdated because gro 4 and claude for
sonnet have come out. So many models
including open source Chinese models
have been used to basically perform this
reasoning or thinking for longer during
inference and the same thing has
actually happened in visions. There's
been lots of interest in scaling
diffusion models at test time as well uh
for image generation or for video
generation. So broad interest from the
field in basically making models perform
better at inference by kind of doing
search or thinking or reasoning or test
time compute whatever you'd like to call
it. But today I'm going to take a
perspective on these approaches that
these approaches are ultimately
unsatisfying in the quest for human
level intelligence. And you might say
why these approaches have had widespread
success. I mean I I use 01 every day and
these models have been largely
successful in doing great in math and
coding benchmarks. So why are these
approaches unsatisfying? And what is my
argument today? Well, from the
intellectual perspective of achieving
human level intelligence, we need
approaches that are modality agnostic
because humans are able to reason and
think over any modality and the current
approaches do not have that
characteristic.
Another challenge is problem
agnosticness. So current approaches very
much rely on especially in language
verifiable rewards i.e. domains or
problems such that they can be easily
verified with a binary reward. An
example of this is coding or math where
we can verify very easily whether or not
a coding or a math solution is correct.
And ultimately this kind of hints at
another problem which is the reliance of
these approaches on external
supervision. So us models or sorry us
humans are able to get to human levels
intelligence without any external
rewards or verifiers or supervision.
we're able to learn how to think on any
modality or any problem without this
type of supervision. So I'm going to
make an argument today that if we want
human level intelligence, right? So if
we want artificial general intelligence
or artificial super intelligence,
whatever you'd like to call it, we
really do need systems that learn to
think on their own on any modality
problem and without any additional
supervision just like us humans, right?
So you might ask, okay, this makes
sense. you know, I want my model to be
modality agnostic, problem agnostic,
supervision agnostic, etc., etc. But how
can I achieve this? Right? The current
paradigm is very much rely on tons of
humans labeling tons of data for
verifiable rewards. Same thing with the
fusion models. They rely on external
verifiers, kind of labeling how good
responses are. So, how can we do this
without external supervision? And the
point that this kind of leads to which
our paper energy based transformers asks
is how can we learn to think from
unsupervised learning. And this is the
goal of today is to demonstrate to you
that we actually can teach models to
learn how to think from unsupervised
learning. And there's a clever way of
doing this, right? And uh we'll kind of
go over that briefly and describe in
detail how that works later on. But the
general idea is in order to do thinking
we generally need a verifier. So we're
going to learn to verify our predictions
and then what we'll do is we'll learn to
optimize predictions with respect to
this verifier right so given a verifier
it can tell me how good any prediction
is with a given context right so given a
sequence and a next distribution
prediction for a language model this
verifier can tell me how good that
distribution is or doing classification
on imageet given an image and a class
that verifier can tell me how good that
class is with the image it turns out
that all these ideas can actually kind
of be summed up in one framework called
energy based modeling. And in the active
inference community, I'm sure many of
you are familiar with this. In the
broader AI community, energy based
models have been less popular. The
general idea is energy based models
frame thinking or system 2 or reasoning
as optimization over what is called a
learned energy landscape. And we'll talk
more in detail about what that means to
train an energy based model.
So I'm going to make everyone in the
next two minutes an expert. Okay. So
what are feed forward models? Feed
forward models generally take the form
for supervised learning of given an
input, given an X, predict a Y hat,
right? So given an image, predict the
images label or given a sequence of
tokens, predict the next token. This is
the way language models work,
classification models work, etc. etc.
The idea behind an energy based model is
that they are given an input X and a
prediction Y had. So for example a
context or a sequence of tokens and a
distribution over next tokens and they
tell you how high energy or low energy
those are. And the general idea is like
low energy is high probability and high
energy is low probability. So high
energy is unlikely or not compatible.
And then this ultimately brings about
the question of okay I've trained this
energybased model. How do I predict
using my energybased model? Right? I
have this X and this Y hat. How do I
predict this Y hat? Because we
ultimately care about using these models
for prediction.
It turns out that there's an elegant way
to do this that's very similar to
diffusion models. The general idea is
this. What we will do is we will start
like diffusion models with a random
prediction. So this Yhat will start as
for example random noise. And what we'll
do is we'll input this yhat into the
model and we'll get the energy of this
yhat right with the context. And ideally
this energy will be very high because
this yhat is not compatible with the
current x. And then what we'll do is
we'll get the gradient from this energy
to this yhat and iteratively refine this
yhat with respect to this energy. So
this is actually doing exactly what we
said earlier which is learning a
verifier which is this energy scaler and
then learning to optimize predictions
with respect to this verifier by
updating y iteratively or updating yhat
iteratively.
And you can kind of visualize this. So
for example if you're training a video
model the initial prediction would be a
random frame. If you're training a
language model the initial prediction
would be a random noise distribution.
And the idea is what you'll do is you'll
feed this into the model, you'll get the
energy and then you'll iteratively
perform energy descent or energy
minimization and you continuously doing
that until convergence.
So I tell people about this and they
often ask me why do we care about
formulating models in this way, right?
Like feedboard models seem much simpler.
With the feedboard model, all we do is
input X and we get Y. Why do we care
about doing this energy minimization
thing? And there's a couple theoretical
perspectives on why this is useful. The
first one is flexibility. So energy
based models are very broad. It turns
out that virtually anything can be any
model can be formulated as an implicit
energy based model. And you're really
just doing density estimation over all
the possible variables. It's very broad.
It's also very theoretically sound. So
we'll kind of talk about this in more
detail later, but one of the huge
theoretical benefits of these energy
based models is that they could
potentially be turn complete per
prediction. Which means that for
predictions that require an inherent
amount of serial computation, energy
based models could actually solve these
problems. Whereas a feed forward model
cannot because feed forward models have
a finite program. Um, energy based
models can also verify predictions with
this energy scaler and can learn
uncertainty in continuous state spaces
pretty easily. So it's very much more
difficult to do this in uh with feboard
models.
And it turns out that energy based
models are a very broad framework. I
kind of hinted at this earlier and I
like to think about energy based models
under two different perspectives.
Explicit energy based models and
implicit energy based models to kind of
clarify this. Um and the reason I say
this is because a lot of models that
exist for example GANs and diffusion
models can actually be seen as implicit
energy based models. So what this means
is models where you can implicitly
derive an energy function but where this
energy function is not an explicit
output of the model. So just want to
clarify that the models that we focus on
in this paper are explicit energy based
models where the entire model given a
set of inputs maps to a single scalar a
scalar field called the energy and
implicit energy based models you need to
do some work to get this scalar energy
and it's worth noting that these
explicit energy based models have never
really worked well right so what I'm
telling you about the attraction of
these energy based models for
verification and prediction and turn
completeness it sounds great but they
never really worked and the general
intuition behind practitioners you know
pursuing energy based models in AI is
like don't they don't work they don't
scale they're unstable there's tons of
issues they're slow etc etc so the goal
of this work the tlddr if I had to give
one would be we want to make energy
based models actually work we want to
make them relevant we want to see how
they scale and we want to make them work
practically so that we can get these
great benefits of dynamic computation
and verification etc etc at inference
And in order to do that, we need a
stable and paralyzable architecture
particularly because energy based models
have very much failed to scale because
of inherent serialness in computation
and non-paralizability as well as
instability. So when people try and
scale energy based models, they tend to
be very unstable and have issues with
the gradient.
And it turns out that transformers are a
great fit. Transformers have amazing
gradient control having a very long
residual stream and there's strong
empirical evidence suggesting that
transformers can scale hugely widely and
you know to multi- trillion parameter
scale regimes.
Okay. So this is why we created energy
based transformers with this natural
synergy and I like to visualize how
energy based transformers look compared
to existing approaches just to
understand like what are the qualitative
differences and I like to think about
this in the perspective of some of the
kind of cognitive facets or abilities we
talked about earlier. So if you have a
feed forward model and we're just
thinking about auto reggressive modeling
for now the amount of computation that
you have for every prediction made i.e.
with like current language models is
fixed. So these have finite depth. The
program ends. The amount of computation
it has is equivalent to the amount of
depth and that's it. You can't use any
more computation for a specific
prediction.
RNN's generally the way that they are
trained currently have the same flaw. So
because we usually train RNNs to only
update their h state given new state
information, they don't have this
ability to dynamically compute um at
least in the current regime for most of
the popular RNN variants um per
prediction. Diffusion models on the
other hand actually do have this
capability. So diffusion models can have
an unbounded amount of computation for
every prediction being made. So that
means essentially that my diffusion
model can d noiseise for an unbounded
amount of time and therefore can be
potentially turn complete. One of the
challenges with diffusion models in
practice theoretically they have this
but in practice they don't really is
being able to verify predictions. So
let's say I generate sample A with my
diffusion model and sample B with my
diffusion model. My diffusion model has
no clue whether sample A or sample B is
better. It generally does not work in
practice. Energy based models actually
can do this. So with an energy based
model, I can generate sample A, generate
sample B, pass both of these into the
model, get a single scalar energy for
both of them, and then use the argument
of the energies to determine which
sample is better.
Okay, so I'm going to dive into quickly
kind of the theoretical properties that
these models have. And feed forward
models per prediction don't really have
many of the properties that would be
desirable for making predictions with
dynamic compute. So feed forward models
per prediction are not turn complete and
they also cannot give likelihoods
without tricks. So particularly in
continuous state spaces um if you're
using a feed forward model you have to
resort to stuff like elbow or vq for
discretization in order to give
likelihoods and this results in kind of
some icky compression and some other uh
undesirable traits. So generally kind of
standard vanilla feed forward models
can't do many of these things in
continuous state spaces. Diffusion
models can be turn complete because they
can have potentially unbounded amount of
computation for making predictions but
in practice they don't verify or give
likelihoods. Um energy based models can
do all these things. So you can run
energy based inference for longer giving
you this turn completeness from a
theoretical perspective and you can also
give relative likelihoods with these
energy based models. So I think it's
also worthwhile to visualize how these
energy based models actually look and
how they perform inference. So this is
an example here of what an energy based
model would learn during training which
we call an energy landscape. And the
idea is this energy landscape is a
highdimensional space spanning your
predictions that tells you it's a scalar
field telling you at each point in this
prediction space how high or low energy
is this essentially how high or low
probability this is based off the
prediction its compatibility with the
context. Right? So let's say we have a
context of the dog caught though. If we
feed in a random noise distribution
prediction, this would likely be high
energy. And the idea would be what
you're doing during inference is you're
performing energy minimization to get to
this local minima which corresponds to
like a local energy minima that is
strong and has a good prediction. This
prediction is a good distribution
corresponding to a token that has high
likelihood under this context. And the
idea is like learning this energy
landscape allows you to dynamically
allocate computation verify predictions
have uncertainty in continuous state
spaces etc etc. Dynamic computation can
be performed by performing energy
minimization for longer prediction
verification can be done by getting the
energy at specific points and
uncertainty can be done with highly
multimodal energy landscapes where if
there's multiple local minima you know
that the model is uncertain about which
prediction is best.
Okay, so I'm going to dive into how
energy based transformers perform in
practice. We did a lot of scaling
results in this paper to kind of dive
into this and to determine whether or
not they actually can scale well. And uh
generally the results were very good,
right? So we tested on a variety of
axes. I'll show parameter scaling and
flop scaling later. But if you just
holding everything else constant, just
changing the amount of data or the batch
size or the depth energy based
transformers scale faster than the
strong transformer plus auto reggressive
baseline. And it's worth noting that
these are auto reggressive energy based
transformers as well. They could be
birectional potentially but be compared
fairly to the transformer plus. And what
we really care about is the slope or the
asmtoic down into the right performance.
And you can see that these energy based
transformers generally have much higher
slope. So as much as like almost 36% for
data scaling and perform better down
into the right. Um which is great.
That's what really matters when you're
scaling these models to foundation model
level compute.
We also did parameter scaling or like
these are commonly referred to as
scaling walls in NLP. Um and you can see
that the trend for energy based
transformers is generally better
especially in uh video for basically
scaling during pre-training.
We also did downstream inference results
uh or what I like to call thinking
scaling and basically testing the
generalization of these models given a
similar pre-training performance. And
you can see that at first the energy
based transformers have more perplexity
degradation which is like corresponding
to performing worse. But when you
basically run these energy based
transformers for longer or have them
think for longer um the performance
actually gets better. So asmtoically
they generalize much better than the
transformer++ by dynamically allocating
more computation.
And then another thing that's great is
like we see many of the metrics that we
care about with these energy based
transformers improving during training.
So verification improves as you train
the longer the model for longer which
essentially means that if you were to
train a foundation model with energy
based transformers the verification
would get better and better during
training which is great for avoiding
avoiding adversarial examples or
generalizing even better during training
time during test time.
We also compared energy based
transformers to diffusion models and
this were birectional variance on like a
simple image denoising task and we can
see that energy based transformers
generally den noiseise much faster
faster i.e be with less forward passes
and have better quality. So the
downstream metrics are better. And one
thing that's really important that I
think is potentially very impactful is
representation learning. And
representation learning with diffusion
models has tend to become tend to be
very difficult and there are a lot of
tricks that you need for representation
learning with diffusion models. With
energy based transformers, we've pretty
easily seen that they learn decent
representations, albeit better than
diffusion models.
One other great property that we kind of
investigated qualitatively was the
ability to learn uncertainty. And the
idea is like and you could do this in
continuous space as well. U we want the
models to know what they don't know. And
this is a huge challenge and perhaps
like why a lot of the current models
struggle at inference and with
hallucination and other stuff like this
because they don't really know what they
don't know. So generalizing out of
distribution tends to require knowing
what you don't know. And we can see here
that energy based transformers have
higher energy for tokens that are harder
to predict. So for example, a quick
brown fox. Same thing with research and
problem here. Whereas tokens that are
easier to predict such as is a but
period have lower energy. So this is
very promising for principal
generalization out of distribution or
for teaching models what they don't
know. Um and that is one of the general
kind of theoretical benefits of energy
based models especially in continuous
state spaces.
Okay,
this wraps up the last of the results.
Now I'm going to transition the talk a
bit and talk a bit about something more
reflective and sort of prospective
prospective based off a lot of the
learnings from this paper. Right? So I
conducted a lot of experimentation for
this paper, lots of scaling runs and I
kind of realized something realized that
there's something deeper going on and
particularly something that is kind of
the whole field is trending towards and
that's what I'm going to talk about. So
if we ask that question where are we
headed right where are models headed as
we train them longer and longer and
there's a trend in all loss plots. So if
we could imagine that we have 10,000
times the amount of computation that we
have now, virtually all models would
approach approximately zero loss or
close to zero loss, right? So given
10,000 times the amount of GPUs instead
of 10,000 GPUs having I don't know 100
billion or whatever, all models will
approach zero loss. And this kind of
looks like this, right? So all models
eventually achieve close to zero loss or
whatever the irreducible slash random
noise or loss correspond to prediction
of random noise is and I kind of like to
visualize that as a perplexity of one or
an MSE of 0.5 here right and in fact I'd
argue that frontier labs are already
starting to achieve this right so
frontier labs are already very much
saying that they are not computebound
but rather that they are data bound that
data is the main issue and what this
kind of signals is most of these models
are achieving close to zero loss, right?
Or potentially what is called the
irreducible loss.
And what this means is that we care much
less when we're not computebound but
rather data bound about convergence
speed. Right? So all these models
regardless of the scaling rate even if
EBTs do scale faster during pre-training
reach the same kind of zero loss or
close to zero loss. Right? So different
journeys but the same destination.
Okay. Okay, so what am I getting to?
Right, this is like approximately zero
loss, irreducible, the best models can
possibly do, etc., etc. What matters
here, right? If models really are
approaching this kind of close to zero
loss regime, what actually matters?
And I kind of hinted at this earlier,
but it's not the scaling rate. So all
models will eventually kind of reach
close to zero loss. All decent models at
least. So the question is like what
matters here? And you might say, what
about inference speed or flops or
latency? And I would also argue that
these don't matter. If we have 10,000
times the amount of computation, models
are already getting close to being able
to run on device with 10,000 times the
amount of compute inference speed and
flops won't really matter. So is our job
done, right? Do we have to do anything
else in this 10,000x compute regime once
our models achieve close to zero loss?
And today I'm going to argue that the
answer is no. And that we have a lot of
work left to do. And this is the insight
that I gained from doing this project.
Right? So there's sort of a secret, an
unspoken secret of AI research that a
lot of the big tech companies don't want
the public to know, which is that zero
training loss does not equal real world
perfection or 100% benchmark saturation
does not equal real world perfection. In
other words, even if your model achieves
100% on every single difficult AI
benchmark there is and does perfect on
your validation set, this model will
still not generalize perfectly out of
distribution. Right? So in other words,
there will always always always be novel
unseen situations in the real world that
your model has to adapt to and then it
has to generalize to. And it turns out
that humans adapting to this novelty is
what we are very good at. Right? So
we're able to generalize every day to
out of distribution scenarios that we
have never seen in our life.
In fact, I really like this example of a
counterintuitive fact about just how
much we generalize. So if you just think
hypothetically for a second about
training a model on all possible human
data. So all video data that humans have
ever seen, all language data that humans
have ever spoke, all audio data, etc.,
etc., right? The crazy thing about this
data is that most of it will still be
out of distribution. Most of this data
will still be very much data that the
model has to generalize to.
In fact, something very interesting is
that you can mathematically guarantee
that this video that you have observed
for the past 5 minutes. This is the
first time you are seeing this video, in
fact, this is the first time anyone in
our universe has ever observed this past
5-minute video that you're observing.
Right? So, this is how highdimensional
the data we are dealing with is. And
that's why this out of distribution
generalization problem is the core
problem that we have with AI right now
and that we'll have to tackle over the
next 10 years.
So what matters in this zero loss regime
I kind of said this earlier is
generalization right so how your model
performs on this out of distribution
data and I like to refer to this as the
era of generalization right so this era
where all models in the frontier labs
are essentially achieving the same
performance or approximately zero loss
what really matters is how well does
your model generalize this kind of
explains why there's been a lot of
interest in reasoning or thinking models
because these models allow for better
generalization at test more
adaptability, more test on compute, more
thinking, etc., etc.
Okay, this brings us to the question
which is if we care about generalization
instead of just flops scaling, how do we
measure it? Right? And today I'm going
to propose a simple metric that I
believe will be more helpful than
relying on many downstream benchmarks.
And that is because downstream
benchmarks tend to be very high bias and
variance, right? So depending on which
benchmarks you use to measure models,
they'll look better or worse. You can
see this in the frontier. You know, the
benchmarks that different companies use
show their bench their models being
better, but oftent times are worse,
etc., etc. So, I'm going to give insight
into a potentially more useful and
practical metric for generalization,
which is data efficiency, right? And
I'll be arguing that data efficiency is
actually a form of generalization. And
the reason for this is if I have given
you three concepts, sorry, three
examples and you were able to learn a
new concept given those three examples,
but it takes me four examples to learn
such a new concept, you have generalized
better, right? So you have used less
data to achieve the same compression
rate or the same representations or
potentially better representations with
less data. So that's data efficiency,
but you've also generalized better. So
given that you keep everything constant,
same metric, same architecture, same
parameter count because you need the
same compression ratio, if you achieve
the same metric during pre-training with
less data, your model is actually
generalizing better. And that's what
I'll argue for here today. Okay, so I've
claimed that data efficiency is how we
will measure generalization and that
generalization is what we should care
about. So this ultimately brings us as
researchers or engineers to the question
of how do we measure models right what
x-axis do we use to measure model
performance
and over the last 5 years it's an x-axis
that looks energy that makes energy
based transformers look very bad which
is flop scaling energy based
transformers needing to do MCMC or
optimization during pre-training are
inherently more expensive although I'm
sure you can make this better but are
inherently more expensive than feed
forward models right and hence why you
see that this flop
uh count is much higher. So you might
say, okay,
these models are terrible for flop
scaling. What about the error of
generalization, right? So what about
when all we really care about is
generalization? If all models achieve
close to the zero loss or close to
approximately zero loss, then what
really matters is not their flop scaling
because all models will eventually
achieve this, but actually their data
efficiency and their generalization. And
I like to propose that we take a look at
this graph and focus more on this over
the next couple years because
generalization is becoming the big
bottleneck.
Okay. Now I'm going to bring the talk
back to a question from the start which
is would you trade off 100x times the
amount of compute for 1% better
generalization? So running your GPUs for
100 times longer. And I hope that under
this perspective under this perspective
that potentially we are in this era of
generalization where the bottleneck
really is just generalizing out of
distribution rather than being more flop
efficient. The answer becomes an
undoubtable yes because generalization
will be all that we care about.
That's it for the presentation. I'm
happy to answer any questions and thank
you very much for listening.
Awesome.
Great talk. Okay. While everyone in the
live chat gets some questions ready and
enters them which I will read to you,
could you just give a little background?
How did you come to this problem? What
about grad school? What was your
trajectory to get to this question and
collaboration?
Yeah, good question. I would say that I
very much started working on energy
based models just from a uh I thought
they were a very intuitive perspective.
So to me, you know, if you ask me like
is the brain doing something more
similar to energy based modeling or feed
forward modeling in no doubt there's no
doubt in my mind that it's more similar
to energy based modeling at least in
some respects. Um particularly with
regards to like some of the capabilities
we talked about, right? So being able to
dynamically allocate computation, verify
predictions, but I think one key thing
is also learning like this joint
distribution over variables. I think
that's very important especially when we
will eventually take these to multimodal
learning to kind of learn like this
compatibility between all the input
variables and like predictions right so
you don't just learn given an image to
map to a classification head it's not
like there's some classification head in
my brain that tells me the logic value
for each class when you're doing image
classification no it doesn't work like
that right you learn this joint
distribution over all the possible
images in all the possible language and
then you learn how compatible these are
right you know whether this image of a
dog is compatible with the word dog you
don't just learn a distribution over the
possible classes so to me they were
always very intuitive and that's kind of
why I started working on them um and
then I saw that there was lots of room
for reasoning with them and uh
eventually started working on them
during around 2 years ago and yeah just
kept working on them for a while and
making them trying making them work and
exploring and yeah now we're here so
that's the the journey very much as
curiosity led
started from the energy maxima now we
here
okay there's so many entry points and
and I'm sure people will have
interesting questions but you brought up
one of the advantages being the
flexibility so what exactly is that
energy landscapes flexibility what data
matters and why what could we say about
What kinds of generalization
would be
in out of distribution scope versus out
of out of distribution scope? Like what
is it about the energy landscape? Do you
just dump random data? Is it about
organic data? What is it that is about
the data? And what does the energy
landscape reflect that would or does
have flexibility?
Yeah. Um
this is a challenging question. I would
say uh the
the general intuition is like this
energy landscape is learned over all
possible values, right? Based off the
data. So your data shapes this landscape
that's learned over all possible
prediction values. And like a feed
forward model doesn't learn this kind of
like uh landscape over all possible
values. It learns a single pointwise
estimate of the prediction. And the
ability to learn kind of this estimate
over all possible predictions rather
than just predicting a single prediction
like a pointwise estimate is what
enables us better generalization because
at test time what you can do is instead
of just giving a point-wise prediction
estimate you can search over these
predictions. Right? So that's what what
you're actually doing with energy
minimization is you're searching over
the prediction space and that's why this
energy landscape is great. And then with
regards to your questions about data um
which data is important uh you know
where can energy based models generalize
better. I would say that in general
energy based models have generalized
better which we show as well as some
other papers show. I think that on
certain tasks energy based models
generalize orders of magnitude better.
So there's this other paper that we cite
that shows that for some synthetic tasks
energy based models can generalize like
10 times better than a feed forward
model because the energy function or
like this verification is very well
defined. So I can give an example of
this which would be solving a maze. So
if you were to generate a solution to a
maze with a feed forward model, you
could imagine the maze is like this and
solving that you need to be able to
predict in a single forward pass all the
different routes or like all the
different turns and everything to solve
this maze. Whereas an energy based
model, this energy function will just
learn whether or not the solution is a
valid solution. That is the solution
verification. And on that problem, it's
much easier to verify than it is to
generate. And because of that, I think
you could see that EBMs would generalize
much better because this energy function
is very well defined. So I would say
that in general, EBMs can generalize
better, but there's certain problems
where they can generalize much better.
And then with regards to the question on
what data can EBMs generalize better on,
um I think that in the short term we'll
see EBMS uh more applicable for data
that is uh for applications where there
is limited data particularly because of
this uh data efficiency that we've seen
with EBMs. And you can train them. They
do require more flops at least in the
short term. But you can train them such
that they kind of learn this energy
landscape over this very limited amount
of data. And because you might have a
limited amount of data, you have tons of
compute uh to work with that data. And
that essentially means that like you can
generalize better out of distribution by
kind of learning this huge distribution
over all possible predictions uh with
this limited data. So I see that as the
primary use case in the short term, but
in the long term I think that most data
we could definitely see EBMs performing
better on. So yeah,
so in the provocative opening question,
at first when I heard it, I was
thinking, oh, this is kind of like a a
Pascal's wager or how many cousins to
save a brother and those kinds of
questions. But then it's like actually
we're if as you're describing looking to
research to where the puck is going and
head to a place if we're not already
past it where compute isn't a limitation
and then it's like yes it is worth it to
spend more compute. So that was just
that was definitely very
counterintuitive but also helps
contextualize. And yet out of that
provocation
are coming models which could be more
efficient per watt and per data set. So
it just is like but that question is the
entry point to understanding what we're
really limited in.
Mhm.
Okay. I'll read a question from the live
chat. So Tucker Chambers wrote,
"Do any current models generalize into
the real world at all? Maybe Tesla
vision-based models have a leg or a
wheel up on the competition as they're
using real world data in the physically
embodied sense."
Yeah. Uh I think this is a debatable
question that depends on who you ask. Um
I mean I think yes some models are
generalizing to the real world. The
question is how well are they
generalizing and are they generalizing
to the point where they are widely
useful.
Robotics is very much unsolved and seems
to be very far from being solved which
is one of the biggest use cases of AI.
you know uh completely autonomous
driving has been promised to be solved
for a long time but it's still unsolved
we still even with like uh Whimo there
are still people watching so I would say
that some models are generalizing but
they are not generalizing as well as
humans would which is the core challenge
is like generalization to the same
extent as humans the same performance um
ideally given the same data although
these models are trained on orders of
magnitude thousands of times the amount
of data that humans have ever seen So,
uh, yeah, I hope that answers your
question. So, they're generalizing, but
not to the extent that we would like.
And then Daniel, I want to kind of hit
on what you said earlier, which is like
this provocative question of is it just
a trade-off or, you know, in this
regime, is it really even a trade-off
anymore? Cuz like if our GPUs are just
idling, if we have 10,000 times the
amount of GPUs, it might not even
matter, right? We might really just say,
okay, we don't care about burning 100
times the amount of GPUs. We really just
care about generalization. So yeah, I
think it's interesting and I think that
um you know, we're definitely not there,
especially in academia right now
everywhere. Maybe the frontier labs are
starting to get there and like people
have said like OpenAI released a video
where they talk about GBT4.5 and they
basically say that and I actually have
this here. Um that we're more data bound
than we are compute bound. Um which is
cool. So I'm sure that many of the
frontier labs are starting to face this
as well. And I think that as this
happens more and more, we'll tend to see
like a shift more toward from like flop
scaling and that being the predominant
thing that people care about to like
data efficiency and generalization
because at the end of the day, what
really matters is how well does your
model generalize once it's gotten to
this point of kind of fitting the
training set already. So yeah,
super interesting. Um, again, anyone can
write more questions in the live chat,
but how about a little bit on the almost
developer experience here? Like, what
was it like
getting those results? Was there a lot
of under the hood and fine-tuning and
what kinds of software and methods are
useful and what are they like today? And
then what kinds of methods could unlock
the amount of attention that's currently
going into alternative methods to make
use of what you're demonstrating in the
paper.
Yeah. So in terms of getting the
results, it was I would say a very
difficult journey mostly because there's
not much practical advice on how to
train energy based models online.
A lot of the work that's out online is
very much theoretical and also hasn't
really been tested at scale. So a lot of
work in this paper that's kind of not
necessarily super cool but is important
nonetheless for uh practicality is just
determining like what hyperparameters
are necessary, how to tweak things so
that things work, what are kind of the
core challenges with stability and what
tricks do you need to solve them. We
have a lot of tricks that we mentioned
in the paper um and that help that you
know help us with stability and can help
with scalability. But I think that this
is one of the key challenges is just
kind of like pretty much all models now
rely on tricks like diffusion models
there's tons of tricks flow models
there's tons of tricks even auto
reggressive models at scale there's tons
of tricks with lair and all this stuff.
So, it's all about really figuring out
like what are the right tricks for these
models and it took a while and it was a
lot of just like kind of banging your
head on the wall and just trying things
out and seeing what sticks. But I think
eventually and to the point where we are
now uh we have hyperparameters and
general tricks that make things work
more generally and we know how to scale
these things. So if you told me to train
a 7B model and you gave me the compute
we could. So I think that once we
started figuring out how to make things
stable and scalable and kind of uh you
know look good without loss spikes or
anything like that the results started
to look really great and that's when we
started to get like really great data
efficiency curves and other stuff like
that and it was super rewarding having
worked on just kind of tuning these
tricks for a very long time. And then
with regards to long-term adoption and
kind of making energy based models
adopted more widely as compared to
something like diffusion models or pure
feed forward auto reggressive models. I
think that there's a couple things that
need to happen. I think one is like it
would be great if a foundation model
energy based model was scale. Um that
way people can really see that these do
work out foundation models scale. our
results is just that you know uh given
extrapolation that things could scale
well but we don't actually know because
we haven't trained them and we didn't
have the computing resources to do that.
So I think kind of at scale would be
nice. Um another thing that would be
helpful is just like more tricks in
tuning with diffusion. I like to bring
up this example where it took lots of
tricks and papers to kind of figure out
like how do I sample from this? How do I
make sampling faster? How do I make them
efficient and more practical etc etc. I
have no doubt that over the next year or
two, lots of effort will go into
basically just having tricks that are
better for these energy based models and
kind of making it so they're faster to
train, faster during inference, etc.,
etc. Um, but I think with those things
and given kind of the way that comput is
headed, there will start to be interest
in the next couple years. So, I'm very
hopeful. Yeah.
Tucker asks a follow-up question there.
Can EBM be built and trained on normal
civilian hardware? Or I guess just more
generally like what kind of hardware
resources within the vonoyman paradigm
are most relevant and what kinds of
unconventional or thermoinformational or
biomimetic computing could be a little
bit on the horizon to go even beyond
that.
Yeah. So I will clarify that um
we focus very much on energy based
models that are you know sort of uh
efficient on vonoyman hardware here. So
that's like models with matrix
multiplications using back propagation.
Um there are other energy based models
or like for example predictive coding
learning algorithm that are uh faster to
implement on other hardware that I'm by
no means an expert. Um so these energy
based models are very much strong on
modern vonoyoman architectures
especially GPUs because everything is
done with matrix multiplications and is
learned end to end with back propagation
which we can compute quickly on modern
hardware. Um so yeah you can definitely
train these energy based transformers on
you know smaller GPUs. They do take more
memory than a feed forward model, but um
you know most of our experiments were
done at very small scale on smaller
GPUs. So you can definitely do this on
potentially laptop GPUs or like a you
know small scale school setup that you
have um for the smaller scale models at
least. So yeah, very uh akin to modern
hardware.
Could we return to the slide with the
architectural
layouts?
Yes, of course.
Actually,
let me just do this.
Okay. Yeah. So, maybe just highlight
what is different here structurally
and then possibly take that towards what
would that look like in practice? Is
this the same chat GBT perplexity
interface that's just doing better but
giving the same kind of result? Is this
like horse and buggy versus car and
we're talking about different kinds of
assessments? Like what is happening
under the hood and structurally? And
then is that a hot swap competing on the
same kinds of measures and input output
structures that we see today with all
the zoo of available models or what
other kinds of harnesses are needed or
functions arise?
Yeah. Yeah. Great question. Uh so I'll
start to dive into the first part which
is like a general overview. Um
so with feed forward models um you'll
get this input X and you'll predict this
like just for auto reggressive modeling
this X hat of T+1 which is like the next
token if you're training a language
model and then you'll back propagate
with an RNN you'll do essentially the
same thing with a diffusion model it's a
little bit different where uh these are
normally not trained auto reggressively
but I kind of visualize that here for
ease of visualization
But um what you'll do is you will take
as input prediction of noise and then
you will essentially predict like this
of noise. Uh so yeah so you'll start
with random noise and you'll predict uh
based off the schedule and like the
current time the score here or like kind
of the dnoising to apply to this xhat of
t+1. Um, and you'll do this for all the
different xhat of t+1's that kind of go
from like pure random noise to uh the
actual data itself. Um, with an energy
based model, it's a lot like a diffusion
model that you initialize this xhat of
t+1 as um or this next token prediction
for language models as random noise or a
random distribution in this case. And
then instead of just predicting the
noise and like subtracting out the
noise, what you'll do is you'll predict
the energy
And then you will get the gradient from
this energy to this prediction, right?
And you'll subtract that gradient out.
So it's just like gradient descent. Um,
and like you'll multiply by step size,
etc., etc. And then you will pass this
back into the model, get the energy
again, update it using the gradient,
etc., etc. And you continue doing this
for every next token at once. So it's
worth noting that we train these as like
GPT2 decoder style language models. So
every single prediction is made at the
exact same time. And that's part of the
a lot of the effort that went into these
like decoder only energy based
transformers.
And yeah, you're basically just
predicting the gradient of every single
next token prediction at the exact same
time using the energy scaler for each
token. Um, yeah. And then in terms of
kind of integrating these things from a
more applied perspective on actual like
applications or in a UI, I see in the
short term very similar applications to
like what we currently see such as like
chat, GPT or perplexity where you're
just doing inference with a language
model. I think that the
in the short term you'll especially see
like hybrid or ensembling of like a feed
forward model with an energy based model
where what you do is you initialize the
prediction with this feed forward model
like initialize the distribution and
then you pass this into the energy based
model and just refine this distribution
right so you're kind of just like u
amortizing a lot of the work that's done
with this energy based model with this
feed forward model or you can consider
ensembling these models um and then uh
another thing that you can do is use
like speculative decoding to kind of
like speed up the uh iterative uh
decoding with these energy based
transformers. So instead of doing every
single next token prediction with these
energy based transformers, have a
lighter weight model and then just check
which logits are kind of or sorry which
distributions are different and sample
that way. So you kind of don't have as
much inference costs cuz they do require
more flops during inference.
Um, and then in the long term, yeah, I
think that there's a couple things that
you could potentially see with energy
based models that you wouldn't be able
to see with these other feed models. One
thing that's exciting is like
compositionality. So, there's been a lot
of work with energy based models and
compositionality. Basically, like
combining different models with
different attributes and generalizing to
something new. This could be something
like, for example, generating new images
or generating new languages or whatever
it is you want to do.
That's one thing that you could see in
terms of applications, but I think in
the short term uh from a practical
perspective, most of what you will see
would just be similar to what you would
see with the feed forward model. It
might also be that the way that you do
inference with these energy based
transformers kind of gives you like a
separate way of reasoning where you're
kind of reasoning through this iterative
optimization rather than in token space
with next token prediction. So the
current models are doing this like next
token prediction uh iterative reasoning
rather than doing it in like in a latent
space. So yeah
what exactly makes a transformer a
transformer such that it could be feed
forward diffusive or energy based and is
that part more durable or could
something else be there in that green
box?
Yes. Um
yeah great question. So I think the
definition of a transformer depends on
who you ask. I would say to me the
general definition is like you have uh
per token level
per token level computation and then
like global sequence mixing via
attention. So every token is operated on
independently besides for attention
where you kind of mix information
globally across the sequence.
Um and then is there different
architectures you can use? Yes, actually
I think that we just focus on
transformers because it's one of the
most popular architectures that has
proven itself to be very successful
across wide modalities and domains etc
etc. Ideally you know you could use any
new architecture with energy based
models that comes out. There's like a
recent paper on auto reggressive units
or like I think they're also called
hnetss um that is like essentially a new
architecture for auto reggressive
modeling and I think it'd be great to
combine these things uh as well as long
as these other architectures are stable
and scalable and parallelizable in
addition to transformers. So I don't
think that energy based models
necessarily need to be paired with
transformers. It's just there's good
synergy here due to the high success of
transformers and high computational
efficiency and stability. So,
makes sense. Could you go to the energy
landscape with the dog catching the
uh Yes. Okay. Yeah.
Okay. Burkers asks, "Do EBM get stuck in
local minima during inference?"
Yes. Yeah, that is a great question. So
the answer is yes. And
unfortunately this is not necessarily
something that is easy to avoid.
But this isn't a huge problem because in
highdimensional spaces there are less
local minima. So it turns out that there
are less local minima and more settle
points. So it's hard to get stuck in
local minima in very high dimensional
spaces. But you are not guaranteed to
converge to a global minimum with these
energy based models. So part of one of
the benefits of sampling many many times
is that you can converge to different
local minima one of which may be your
global minimum and then you use this as
your response. So I think it would be
interesting to try and kind of enforce
some constraints to actually I don't
think it's possible to enforce
constraints to have a single global
minima because then you would restrict
the expressivity of your model and you
wouldn't be able to kind of fit very
highdimensional data. But it it's very
uh it's a difficult problem and there's
lots of theoretical work broadly on MCMC
and kind of converging to the the best
minima. So yeah,
definitely
um there's problems/data sets that are
easy and monotonic and there's ones that
are wickedly designed. You brought up
MCMC and you mentioned sampling as well.
So how do you see sampling based
approaches with variational
optimizationbased incremental
approaches? Where where do sampling
particlebased distributionbased methods
come into play? How do we know where to
use different balances of those?
Yeah. Uh I'm not an expert on this. I'll
preface with that. But um I think that
all of these are pretty like
disjoint from this work and then not
disjoint I should say like compatible
with this work and sort of adjacent
slash like not necessarily in conflict
too. So you can in principle use
particle based approaches or other more
complex MCMC samplers to sample from
your EBM like one example would be using
HMC Hamiltonian Monte Carlo to kind of
sample better. We just use first order
information or like longon dynamics but
you could in principle use more complex
samplers as well as particle based
algorithms to sample better. Um you can
kind of consider that what we are doing
I'm forgetting the name uh by sampling
many times and choosing the minimum
energy is sort of it's like there's some
reference to this in statistical physics
um you can also use many of the ideas
from statistical physics and kind of
like inspiring better inference or
sampling algorithms where you like
anneal the step size where you like
determine whether or not the energy
decreases and then if it increased like
decrease the step size so you kind of
better get to local minima. Um there's
tons of ways you can do it and I think
that broadly you know this work and the
work on MCMC can only help each other
basically. So uh they're sort of
adjacent and can help in tandem. Yeah.
Yeah. I agree with that. There's um work
on stein mixture models and particle
transport and accelerated
optimization on different kinds of
information geometries. It's kind of
just like exciting how it's all coming
together. So what one reflection which
I'd be curious to hear your thoughts
seeing from an academia researchy and
from an industry side is like in the
datadriven or databased approach there
is some extent data maybe you can
acquire more but it's about doing
something with that data whereas on at
least in the act of inference
computational psychi ry cognitive
modeling space. Often it's more like a
priori systems modeling where we're
designing that joint generative model.
But an empirical data
set doesn't actually have to come into
play. You might be interested in just
abonio modeling of a cognitive agents
and generating synthetic data. And then
there's methods for tuning the
parameters to recapitulate empirical
parameters. But it's just sort of
interesting to see the difference
between having an extent data set as
like the block of marble that you want
to do the best on. like you have a
language corpus and you want it to be
fluent and write awesome PhD
dissertations, but not much structural
information about linguistics has to be
encoded. And that's the sort of stoastic
parent type critique perspective.
Yeah.
In comparison or in complement to making
models who structurally embody
linguistic constraints.
Mhm. and using that to then meet in the
middle. Also, you'd hope with reasonable
looking linguistic expression, but that
approach wouldn't necessarily need to be
trained from unstructured text corpuses.
So if we're thinking about general
purpose EBMS or domain specific EBMS,
you know, arbitrarily narrow to
arbitrarily broad,
where is that going to be from just
dumping a blob of data, setting the
number of parameters and some other
aspects kind of like how vision neural
networks might work. Just here's my data
folder, here's the architecture.
Now go
and where is it going to take more of a
scaffolded
structured approach
that
has a model that embodies aspects of the
situation.
Yeah.
Yeah. That is very hard. I think that
it's very dependent on the amount of
data that you have and the problem. I
think there are certain problems where
you need a prior and that without this
prior you sort of or some inductive bias
with your model to be more data
efficient such that without this
inductive bias you will not succeed and
I think that particularly we'll see that
more often on domains with limited data
right so if you have very limited data
having just a model and just the data no
prior on the structure or inductive
biases of model, your model will very
much overfit that data and not
generalize.
I think the reason that we're able to do
this with language and video and audio
is because we have huge amounts of data.
I mean data that is on orders of
magnitude more than any human will ever
read or see in their lifetime.
So it may very well be that when we
actually care about um well we do care
about this but when we care very much
about achieving human level intelligence
given the same amount of data as humans
we need stronger priors on architecture
and structure
etc. It may also be that from a
practical perspective these are more
useful on specific modalities or domains
where we don't have as much data as we
do for language or for video. So for
example for medical data I am not an
expert on this but I very much believe
that there is many more data constraints
with medical data than there is with
just general videos online or general
language online. And because of this it
may be that you know inductive prior or
kind of structures in your model that
are more akin to how human cognition
works or however your model of you know
psychology works. um are much better at
making decisions and performing or
generalizing. So I think the key is
really data. You know if you have
infinite data you don't need any priors.
You just learn everything from the data.
If you don't have infinite data then
priors are helpful. And this is kind of
broadly what we've observed in AI in the
last decade where over time the amount
of priors that these models have has
decreased and you really just like let
the model fit the data. You don't really
make any assumptions.
um you know 10 years ago or 15 years ago
when we didn't have that much data in
compute people did a lot of hand tweaked
things and engineering and feature
engineering etc etc for their vision
models to make them work better and they
did work better with those hand
engineered features at the time so I
think the the key is like how much of a
bottleneck is your data
I believe I resonate with you on that
with this sort of zigzagging forward
moving pendulum between expert systems
focus so-called and more unstructured
and to combine the structured and the
unstructured is the chocolate chip
cookie that has these kind of neuros
symbolic hybrid synthetic intelligence.
There's just a million ways to point at
these architectures that have different
sorts of elements ranging from logical
discrete to interpolated continuous. So
that's awesome. Um, okay. Last sort of
two areas that I'd love to hear your
take on and then I'll see if there's any
final comment in the in the uh live chat
would be how would somebody who's
wanting to learn and apply get
onboarded? What resources did you all
provide in the repository? And what
kinds of things would somebody want to
learn up on and train up on to be able
to replicate and extend? And then of
course, where is this all going? What is
the next shoe to drop? What is the next
pheromone that will be deposited?
Yeah, I like that last question a lot.
Um, with the first question, yeah, we
tried to make it a little bit easier to
get started. So, at the end of the
paper, like section, I think uh H and I,
there's some intro to EBM tutorial and
stuff like that and some pseudo code.
Um, there's also some videos by Yannik
Kilchure. He's a YouTuber that he made
on energy based models that I think are
really great for getting started. But I
recommend like checking out those videos
and checking out those bladder sections
in the paper that are sort of more
easily written cuz I found it even for
me, you know, like I've been doing EBMs
for a while very difficult to read a lot
of the literature because it's super
theoretical and sort of like maybe not
catered towards beginners. So I think
that you know just maybe checking this
out or checking out some intro or
tutorials on EBMS would be great as well
as just pietorch in general. Um yeah the
yaniculture videos are great as well.
And then the second question where where
are we headed
yeah that is a great question. Um,
I think in the long term, like what
we'll see with diffusion models is kind
of like what we saw with or sorry, what
we'll see with energy based models is
kind of like what we saw with diffusion
models where like at first they're kind
of like, oh, these are impractical. No
one's going to use these to like, okay,
maybe there's some promise to like,
okay, these have narrow applications to
like, oh wow, we can apply these to
almost everything. um like now diffusion
language models are very much becoming
very popular when it used to just be
image generation and now they're used
for planning and robotics etc etc. I
think we'll see the same thing with
energy based models where over time they
will become more and more widespread
because of you know potentially better
generalization. So I think that that is
the future. I think the question is
really like how much time how much
compute do we need and what are the the
kind of core tricks and algorithms you
know and the improvements that can be
made. So that is what I see but I think
that if you believe that generalization
will be the blocker in the next decade
for sure energy based models are a good
way good bet to place your money on. So
if you generalize from your past
experience
to update your belief that
generalization is an important belief to
have updated too.
This is an interesting architecture.
Yeah.
But yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I
agree with that.
Um any final comments or just what's
next for you and your graduate and
beyond adventures?
Um,
not much final comments. Just thank you
guys for the the interest and it's been
kind of amazing. I did not expect as
many people to be interested in the
paper. So, it's super super grateful for
people even listening and for giving me
the time to speak. Um, in terms of my
future, uh, yeah, we'll have to see.
It's it's hard to know. I mean, I I
definitely plan to continue working on
EBMs, but um yeah, I have some some
crazy ideas planned in the future as
well, so we'll see how how those go.
Amazing. Thank you. Super informative.
There's really a big community of
researchers and people kind of in the
engine room and I think also broader and
broader peripheries of interest from
everything AI ethics and just the future
of what is going to happen. So, it's
awesome to see and I hope we can have a
follow-up.
I hope so as well. And yeah, thank you
so much for having me. Really appreciate
it.
All right. Peace. Thank you.
Bye.